Guide to the Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk Records TAM.159
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk Records
Bulk, 1946-1950
1946-1992, bulk 1946-1950
TAM.159
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.25 linear feet in 3 manuscript boxes.
George Polk was a CBS news correspondent covering the Greek civil war who was murdered in Salonika on May 16th, 1948. In the course of his investigations, he had uncovered, and was about to publish, evidence of criminal activity by rightist forces who had the support of the United States and Great Britain. The Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk was founded in 1948 at the initiative of the New York Chapter of the Newspaper Guild. Several people associated with the Greek Communist Pary were convicted of involvement in the murder of Polk in a trial and verdict now widely believed to be fraudulent. The collection contains correspondence, clippings, reports, and a transcript of the trial of Gregorios Stahtopoulos and Anna Stahtopoulos, accused of complicity in the murder. There are also photographs of George Polk and some Price family memorabilia. Correspondents include: John Donovan, William Donovan, Ernest Hemingway, Walter Lippman, Herbert Mitgang, Edward Morrow, George Polk, Rhea Polk, William Polk, Constantine Poulos, William Price, Howard Smith, and I.M. Stone.
Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk (William Price Papers) was donated to the Archives of the Tamiment Library in 1995 by William Price, cousin of George Polk.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note:
On May 16, 1948, the body of George Polk, at the time the Middle East correspondent for CBS, was found floating in the harbor of the Northern Greek city of Salonika. He had been shot in the head and his hands and feet were firmly bound. Polk had been in Greece covering the Civil War between the Communist Forces entrenched in the North and led by Markos Vafiades and the Monarchist-Fascist government dominated by the army. Polk had been critical not only of the Greek government but also of the newly released Truman Doctrine which made defeating the Communists in Greece a priority. In an article published in Harper's in December 1947, Polk called the $300 million in aid to Greece "a poor investment." Most importantly, Polk claimed, the money was being terribly misused. Indeed, immediately before his murder, Polk, in an interview with Constantine Tsaldaris, the head of the Royalist Party, threatened to expose Tsaldaris' illegal bank accounts in the United States. Polk's widow, Rea Polk, later claimed: "I am surprised he lived for three days after that interview."
When Polk was murdered he had been traveling north in an attempt to make contact with General Markos. Polk had been last seen on May 9. The Greek government immediately accused the Communists of the murder. Major Nicholas Mouscoundis, the head of the Greek investigation of the murder, announced that he was "1,000%" sure the Communists had killed Polk. In a trial now considered a sham, a Greek Communist Gregorios Stahopoulos and his mother Anna were convicted of complicity.
In response to the murder and the tainted investigation, the Newspaper Guild organized the Newsmen's Commission in 1948. Among its members were William Polk, George Polk's brother, and William Price, Polk's cousin, and the United Nations Correspondent for the Daily News. Among the known journalists who lent their name, time, and support for the Commission were Ernest Hemingway and Homer Bigart.
Another investigative committee led by Walter Lippmann and called the Overseas Writers Special Committee to Inquire Into the Murder of George Polk was also organized. It later endorsed the trial verdict--a verdict questioned by the Commission. As a result, many Commission members, including William Price, were later officially blacklisted.
Sources:
Chatzeargyres, Kostas. He hyothese Polk: ho rolos ton Xenon Hypersion sten Hellada. Athens: Ekd. Eirene, 1988.
Keeley, Edmund. The Salonika Bay Murder: Cold War Politics and the Polk Affair. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1989.
Marton, Kati. The Polk Conspiracy: Murder and Cover-Up in the Case of CBS News correspondent George Polk. New York: Farrar Straus, Giroux, 1990.
Vlanton, Elias. Who Killed George Polk?: The Press Covers Up a Death in the Family. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1996.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials about the murder of George Polk and the Newsmen's Commission. The collection also includes personal papers of George Polk, William Polk, and William Price. A George Polk series includes a selection of personal papers of George Polk, including financial papers and correspondence and his naval service records. Much of the collection is devoted to documents about the murder--including press releases and reports--and the trial. Especially significant are copies of the indictment of Gregorios and Anna Stahtopoulos and trial summaries and notes. One of the selection of notes are William Polk's, detailing the trial proceedings and his personal reactions.
The selection of materials on the Newsmen's Commission itself documents its fundraising and publicity. Materials include fundraising letters and receipts, correspondence, and press releases. Also of importance are debates and resolutions within the Newspaper Guild and the United Nations Correspondents about the level of support for the Commission.
Additionally, there are approximately 120 images (photocopies, photographs, and negatives). Image subject matter includes Polk's careers in the military and journalism, events surrounding Polk's murder and the investigation, and Polk's family.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The collection is organized into eight series (see container list, below): I. Greek Civil War; II. George Polk; III. Polk Murder; IV. Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk; V. William Price; VI. William Polk; VII. Name Files; VIII. Photographs.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The John Poulos & Constantine Poulos Papers: Greek and Greek-American radicalism collection
CBS News.; CBS Television Network.; Committee of Overseas Writers to Inquire into the Murder of George Polk.; Daily news (New York, N.Y.).; Donovan, John.; Donovan, William.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Kommounistikon Komma tēs Hellados.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Mitgang, Herbert.; Murrow, Edward R.; Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk.; Polk, George, 1913-1948.; Polk, Rhea.; Polk, William Roe, 1929-; Poulos, Constantine, 1916-1986; Price, William Addison, 1915-2009; Smith, Howard K. (Howard Kingsbury), 1914-2002; Stahtopoulos, Anna; Stahtopoulos, Gregorios.; Stone, I. F. (Isidor F.), 1907-; United Nations.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Cold War.; Communists |z Greece.; Correspondence.; Foreign correspondents |z United States.; Greece |x History |x Civil War, 1944-1949 |x Journalists.; Journalists |z United States.; Minutes.; Photographic prints.; Press releases.; Reports.; Transcripts.; Trials (Murder) |z Greece.; War correspondents |z United States.
- Series I: Greek Civil War
  - American Council for a Democratic Greece, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daily Press Review, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greek Civil War, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: George Polk
  - Broadcasts, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Middle East Mosaic(title of planned book), 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Navy, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series III: Polk Murder
  - CBS, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - CBS-Views of the Press, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press Reports, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report of the Overseas Writers of the Special Committee to Inquire Into the Murder at Salonika Greece, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Researcher's Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Resolutions, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - State Department, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trial-Indictment, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Trial-Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Trial-Summaries (English), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Trial-Transcripts (Greek), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series IV: Newsmen's Commission to Investigate the Murder of George Polk
  - General, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finances, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising-Receipts, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Guild, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Report, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - United Nations Correspondents, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Washington Reports, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series V: William Price
  - Correspondence, 1947-1949, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lowell Limpus, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Guild-Elections, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Family, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Polk Award, 1948-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series VI: William Polk
  - Correspondence, 1946-1952 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - William Price and William Polk-Correspondence, 1949-1955, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Condolence Letters, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Memorandum, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Misc., 1948-1984, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trial Notes, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Name Files
  - Shana Ager Alexander, 1948, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Homer Bigart, 1948, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Winston Burdett, 1948, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - John Donovan, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - William Donovan, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Howard Dratch, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ernest Hemingway, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Marcelle Hitschmann, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Herbert Mitgang, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Edward Murrow, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Adelaide Roe Polk, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Rea Polk, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Constantine Poulos, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Howard K. Smith, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - I.F. Stone, 1984, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Elias Vlanton, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series VIII: Photographs (Box 3, Folder 19-29)